All right! Today's דף daf is ק"ב, kuf bet, 102. So again,
דף ק"ב, daf kuf bet, but we start at the bottom of
ק"א עמוד ב', kuf aleph amud bet, תנו רבנן. tana rabanan. Okay,
so we've discussed the debate about whether גיד הנשה gid hanasheh applies
to the children of יעקב Yaakov or not, and now we are
going to have a similar discussion, or not similar, and about whether
it applies to non-kosher animals, and now we're going to have a
similar discussion about אבר מן החי. ever min hachai. So תנו רבנן,
tana rabanan, our rabbis taught. אבר מן החי ever min hachai is
the five lines from the bottom on ק"א עמוד ב'. kuf aleph
amud bet. אבר מן החי נוהג בבהמה חיה ועוף בין טמאין בין
טהורין דברי רבי יהודה. ever min hachai noheg bivehemah chayah ve'of bein
tme'in bein tehorin divrei Rabi Yehudah. So אבר מן החי ever min
hachai applies to whether it is a domesticated animal, like cows and
sheep, whether it's a חיה, chayah, things like deer, or even birds.
גיד הנשה gid hanasheh does not apply to birds because they don't
have a כף הירך, kaf hayerech, like that rounded side.
But אבר מן החי ever min hachai applies to birds, בין טמאין
בין טהורין, bein tme'in bein tehorin, whether kosher or non-kosher, דברי רבי
יהודה. divrei Rabi Yehudah. That is רבי יהודה. Rabi Yehudah. So the
same רבי יהודה Rabi Yehudah that says גיד הנשה gid hanasheh applies
to non-kosher animals, says אבר מן החי ever min hachai applies to
non-kosher animals as well.
For a בן נח? ben Noach? Both בן נח ben Noach and
ישראל. Yisrael. Yeah. We'll discuss בן נח ben Noach in a minute,
but without being stated otherwise, in general, we're assuming we're talking about
Jews. So therefore but they're also prohibited in אבר מן החי, ever
min hachai, so that applies even to non-kosher animals, you get two
prohibitions, so we'll talk about איסור חל על איסור issur chal al
issur in a minute.
ודברי רבי יהודה ורבי אליעזר. vedivrei Rabi Yehudah veRabi Eliezer. Here רבי
אליעזר Rabi Eliezer agrees with רבי יהודה. Rabi Yehudah. So it's not
just the רבי יהודה Rabi Yehudah of גיד הנשה, gid hanasheh, it's
also רבי אליעזר. Rabi Eliezer. וחכמים אומרים, vachachamim omrim, but the sages
say, באלו לא נוהג אלא בטהורין. b'elu lo noheg ela bitehorin. Only
applies by kosher animals. Now we're going to see, again, the same
way by גיד הנשה. gid hanasheh. Is it because of a problem
of איסור חל על איסור, issur chal al issur, a general problem
of שני איסורין, shnei isurin, or is it because the implication of
the verse is this is a prohibition on a type of an
animal that otherwise would be kosher, which is what we said also
by non-kosher animals, way of understanding it. An animal which you could
eat the meat, don't eat the גיד. gid. So maybe it's the
same point about אבר מן החי. ever min hachai. So we'll have
to see. אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabi Yochanan, so said רבי יוחנן,
Rabi Yochanan, ושניהם מקרא אחד דרשו, ushneihem mikra echad darshu, they both
are interpreting one verse, but it's a question about how to interpret
the verse. What's the verse? רק חזק לבלתי אכול הדם, Rak chazak
levilti achol hadam, only strengthen yourself not to eat the blood, כי
הדם הוא הנפש, ki hadam hu hanefesh, the blood is the life
force, is the soul, ולא תאכל הנפש עם הבשר. velo tochal hanefesh
im habasar. And that is the prohibition of אבר מן החי, ever
min hachai, interestingly, notice they didn't mention a limb. Why did the
גמרא Gemara drop the ו? vav? I don't know.
There is a ו vav in the פסוק, pasuk, right? Okay, yeah.
Anyway, I don't know. The גמרא Gemara I think quotes it later.
Anyway, so that prohibition is understood to prohibit אבר מן החי ever
min hachai and בשר מן החי. basar min hachai. Now, we'll although
we'll see a little bit more about that later.
But with the ו, vav, because without the ו vav it sounds
like a separate, it could be interpreted as a separate prohibition. Right,
it wouldn't be connected to the blood.
That's a good point, and we'll see that that's part of the
debate. Now, ולא תאכל הנפש עם הבשר, velo tochal hanefesh im habasar,
don't eat the soul with the meat, it could mean if you
were just reading it and maybe there is also the point about
the dropping of the ו. vav. The נפש nefesh could be the
דם, dam, הדם הוא הנפש. hadam hu hanefesh. So don't eat the
blood with the meat means get the blood out of the meat,
and don't eat the blood. But חז"ל Chazal understand it that that
is a separate prohibition, it's about eating the meat while there's still
a life force in the animal, which is בשר מן החי. basar
min hachai. Don't eat ולא תאכל הנפש עם הבשר, velo tochal hanefesh
im habasar, don't eat wait don't don't eat the life force, no
longer about blood, right as exactly the point, not like the previous
verse, no longer about don't eat the life force, you know, with
the meat, the meat should not be eaten when the life force
is still in the animal. That's that would be בשר מן החי.
basar min hachai.
But it doesn't say the life force is in the blood?
Yeah, that's the exact shift that the גמרא Gemara is doing. Although
the previous verse is about the blood, now it's shifting to talking
about a problem about meat or limb ripped from an animal while
it's alive, and reading נפש nefesh to mean more directly life, not
blood.
And you're distinguishing between בשר מן החי basar min hachai and אבר
מן החי?
ever min hachai? Yes, בשר מן החי basar min hachai and אבר
מן החי ever min hachai are different prohibitions. Yeah, we're going to
discuss it in later in today's דף, daf, but at least one
simple difference is how much you have to eat. בשר מן החי
basar min hachai you'd have to eat a כזית k'zayit of meat.
אבר מן החי ever min hachai you would have to eat a
כזית k'zayit of the אבר, ever, but it can include bones and
sinews and other types of things, and it would also have to
be a whole אבר. ever. If you ate a half of an
אבר, ever, you wouldn't transgress.
You'd transgress בשר basar then?
If you ate a כזית k'zayit of בשר. basar. Now, so the
other way of how you get אבר מן החי ever min hachai
from this verse is a little less clear, but the basic way
is that נפש nefesh is also understood to be a limb, because
a limb has like independent significance to it, and רש"י Rashi says
that if a limb is cut off it doesn't grow back, so
in that way it's sort of similar to a life. Anyway, somehow
we get from this also don't eat בשר מן החי, basar min
hachai, don't eat אבר מן החי. ever min hachai. And now the
question is, we'll get to it later, okay? Now, the question is
how does it relate to the verse about not eating the blood
and the end of the verse about the meat? Assuming that נפש
nefesh here somehow means the limb. So you have before it blood
and after it meat and the limb is in the middle. So
the question is which one of those two is it connected to?
Let's take a look. רבי יהודה ורבי אליעזר סברי, Rabi Yehudah veRabi
Eliezer savri, רבי יהודה Rabi Yehudah and רבי אליעזר Rabi Eliezer are
of the opinion, כל שאתה מצווה על דמו אתה מצווה על אבריו.
kol she'atah metzuveh al damo atah metzuveh al evarav. Any animal whose
blood you can't eat, you can't eat their limbs. והני טמאין, ve'hani
tme'in, non-kosher animals נמי, nami, also, אתה מצווה על דמם, atah metzuveh
al damam, you can't eat the blood of non-kosher animals, it's also
prohibited in the prohibition of blood. Okay. אתם מצווה על אברים, atam
metzuve al evarin, you're also prohibited to eat the אבר מן החי,
eiver min hachai, and for whatever reason we're not concerned about איסור
חל על איסור, issur chal al issur, it certainly is not categorically
excluded, it's included the same way blood of non-kosher animals is included,
which makes sense cause if you think about the problem of אבר
מן החי eiver min hachai it should certainly be at just as
present by non-kosher animals. ורבנן סברי, Verabbanan savri, but the rabbis are
of the opinion, no, they look at the end of the verse.
לא תאכל הנפש עם הבשר, Lo tochal hanefesh im habasar, don't eat
the soul with the meat, meaning don't eat the soul, meaning don't
eat the limb when the soul is still in the animal. אלא
בשר לחודא, Ela basar lechuda, eat the meat when the soul isn't
in the animal. So the problem is don't eat it when the
animal's still alive, but the implication is you could eat it after
you've shechted the animal. So therefore it's only prohibited by an animal
that you would be otherwise allowed to eat. כל שבשרו מותר אתם
מצווים על אבריו, Kol shebasaro muttar atam metzuve al evarav,
if the meat is permissible then don't eat it while the animal
is still alive, don't eat it when you've have a torn limb.
וכל שאין בשרו מותר אי אתה מצווה על אבריו, V'chol she'ein basaro
muttar i attah metzuve al evarav, when the meat is not permissible
you are not prohibited against it because anyway you're not supposed to
be eating this animal regardless. So very much a categorical exclusion like
we had by גיד הנשה. gid hanasheh. גיד, Gid, only something that
you could eat the meat, don't eat the גיד. gid. Only something
you could eat the meat, don't eat a limb that's ripped off
while it's still alive. Okay, now it doesn't mean that somehow the
same way by גיד gid somehow it wouldn't be also symbolically by
a non-kosher animal, or it doesn't mean by אבר מן החי eiver
min hachai there wouldn't be the sort of moral conceptual problem, but
also there's no need to prohibit it, something that anyway you would
think you have a right over and an ability to eat and
consume, even there there're going to be restrictions. Don't eat the גיד,
gid, don't eat the אבר eiver and so on. Yes.
This goes back to what Charlie said yesterday about בני נח bnei
Noach are not permitted to eat אבר מן החי eiver min hachai
from a non-kosher animal. Correct. And we are permitted.
We're not permitted to eat it, to eat it is because of
non-kosher. It's not a double עבירה, aveirah, it's a single עבירה. aveirah.
Worse for them. It's not worse for them, they don't have the
עבירה aveirah of non-kosher animals, so we each get one, we each
only get one demerit.
It's the same, we get the prohibition of non-kosher animals, they get
the prohibition of אבר מן החי. eiver min hachai.
אבר מן החי Eiver min hachai is weightier isn't it?
No. It's prohibited to בני נח bnei Noach but it's not weightier.
No.
It's considered such a major thing.
Maybe morally, maybe sort of in terms of a taboo, but in
terms of its formal weight it isn't. Okay, yeah. All right,
okay.
ורבי יהודה, V'Rabbi Yehuda, says the גמרא Gemara now, למה לי קרא?
lama li kra? Now why does Rabbi Yehuda need a verse to
tell you that you have אבר מן החי eiver min hachai applying
to non-kosher animals? ליתי איסור אבר ליחול על איסור טומאה? Leiti issur
eiver liychol al issur tumah? Why doesn't the prohibition, meaning it should
just be a natural thing, you have the prohibition of non-kosher animals,
now you rip the limb off, the prohibition of אבר מן החי
eiver min hachai should come and take effect on top of it.
He should not be bothered by איסור חל על איסור issur chal
al issur and should not even need a special verse. Why should
he not be bothered by it? Because he should say שכן איסור
נוהג בבני נח, sheken issur noheig bivnei Noach,
because the same way he said, now this is again the
play, the משנה Mishna said that Rabbi Yehuda said שכן איסור נוהג
בבני יעקב, sheken issur noheig bivnei Yaakov, the children of Jacob were
prohibited. The גמרא Gemara reframed it as בני נח. bnei Noach. Now
by גיד הנשה gid hanasheh presumably it didn't literally mean it because
nobody ever said גיד הנשה gid hanasheh applies to בני נח, bnei
Noach, but it meant that prior to being בני ישראל bnei Yisrael
it applied and therefore it's weightier. Here the גמרא Gemara does literally
mean it. אבר מן החי Eiver min hachai applies to non-Jews, בני
נח, bnei Noach, and therefore there shouldn't be a problem of one
prohibition taking place on top of another. Remember when, what is the
case where almost everybody agrees that one prohibition can take place on
top of another? When the second one is an איסור כולל, issur
kolel, a more inclusive prohibition. So I just had this camel, it
was just prohibited to me. Now a limb is ripped off, אבר
מן החי, eiver min hachai, it is prohibited to all non-Jews. So
since it has a wider scope it also can become prohibited to
me as well for the second, for this other reason of אבר
מן החי, eiver min hachai, איסור חל על איסור. issur chal al
issur. So we know that Rabbi Yehuda by דרש drash even by
גיד הנשה gid hanasheh which its just point was that it was
prohibited to the children of יעקב, Yaakov, that was weighty enough to
lead for it to be taking effect on top of the prohibition
of camel. So certainly something like אבר מן החי eiver min hachai
which is prohibited currently to all בני נח bnei Noach should certainly
be a larger prohibition and be able to take effect even for
me and be a double prohibition. And once that's true who needed
a verse to say it? You could have just known it based
on basic principles. Now I want to say one thing before we
see the גמרא's Gemara answer, let me read the answer and then
I'll go back and say the one thing. So the גמרא Gemara
says אין הכי נמי, ein hachi nami, you know what? You're right.
According to Rabbi Yehuda because it's larger scope you didn't even need
a פסוק, pasuk, of course אבר מן החי eiver min hachai took
effect. וכי איצטריך קרא, V'chi itzterich kra, what do you need the
verse for? לרבי אליעזר. L'Rabbi Eliezer. Remember this is the position both
of Rabbi Yehuda and Rabbi Eliezer. Here Rabbi Eliezer was a new
name introduced. We don't know that Rabbi Eliezer normally allows one prohibition
on top of another, even of a larger scope. We don't know
that about Rabbi Eliezer. So for
Rabbi Eliezer you need a verse.
Whatever you hold about איסור חל על איסור. issur chal al issur.
Now before we go on let me just point out that yesterday
I spoke about larger scope in two ways. One is more objects
like on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, not only is נבילה nevela prohibited
all food is prohibited, or when I become טמא, tamei, not only
is this meat in front of me which was already טמא tamei
prohibited but all קרבן korban meat is prohibited, so more objects become
prohibited. And then there's another type of larger scope which is like
this of בני נח Bnei Noach where more people become prohibited. Okay,
so I was first pro- it was just first I was or
Jews were prohibited in this camel, now all people are prohibited in
this limb because it was ripped off. Another example would be in
terms of sexual acts like if a case was a man with
his sister and then she gets married, so she becomes now doubly
forbidden to him because first she was just forbidden to him but
permissible to other men. Now that she's married she's also forbidden to
all other men. So the fact that her status as a married
woman right is now creates a much larger prohibition on a much
larger group of people for the brother now becomes- it's now a
double prohibition. Okay so that is so that's for double מלקות malkus
and double חטאת chatas or whatever the case for sin offering. Now
yesterday I said that just so you understand how what
איסור כולל issur kolel is more objects are prohibited, איסור מוסיף issur
mosif is a little bit debated רש״י Rashi wants to say just
weightier איסורים issurim is איסור מוסיף issur mosif but more classically or
more sort of clearly and consensus wise איסור מוסיף issur mosif is
this second category of not more objects are prohibited but more people
are prohibited.
Okay. Artificial category.
What? Yeah. Why's it an artificial category?
Because to the one person, to the man, to the woman's brother,
yes, but it's not because other people are now included, it's because
a new איסור issur has- has-
yes but normally we say אין איסור חל על איסור. ein issur
chal al issur. Once it's prohibited one way it doesn't become prohibited
another way. Right. Same act. Okay. Right. It's not a totally different
act. Right. Exactly. Okay so just so you understand you know the
גמרא Gemara doesn't introduce the phrase איסור מוסיף issur mosif here but
just since we're being introduced a lot to איסור חל על איסור
issur chal al issur you should know these are the basic two
categories that make- that mostly agreed makes
one to take effect on top of another
and
then the
third one
of איסור חמור, issur chamur, weightier. But weightier does not mean bigger
scope. Weightier because it's forbidden in הנאה, hana'ah, weightier because you get
כרת, kares, weightier because it once applied to the children of יעקב
Yaakov before it applied to בני ישראל. Bnei Yisrael. Those are secondary
considerations, the basic considerations are larger scope. So the גמרא Gemara says
that even if normally you don't hold like רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
by גיד הנשה Gid Hanasheh and da da da and maybe you
don't even hold that larger scope is enough, here there's a special
here by אבר מן החי eiver min hachai in a camel, A
you have larger scope and B you have a special פסוק passuk
linking it to blood which says that it applies the same way
blood applies to non-kosher animals. You had a question Dov? No.
Okay. Yes. So I just, maybe you're going to get into it
later, but how are they actually literally translating the words to get
into this? That לא תאכלו נפש עם הבשר lo tochlu nefesh im
habasar means don't take an אבר מן החי, eiver min hachai, don't
take an אבר מן החי eiver min hachai the
נפש עם הבשר nefesh im habasar while while sort of נפש nefesh
is read both ways while the life force is still in the
meat.
How do you get limb out of that?
נפש nefesh representing the limb, רש״י Rashi says, the same way like
limb doesn't a life doesn't come back a limb that's torn off
doesn't recede.
It should've been לא תאכלו הבשר עם הנפש lo tochlu habasar im
hanefesh not הנפש עם הבשר. hanefesh im habasar.
לא תאכלו הנפש
lo
tochlu
hanefesh don't eat the limb עם הבשר im habasar when the life
force still exists in the meat. When there's- when הנפש עם הבשר.
hanefesh im habasar.
לא תאכלו נפש עם הבשר.
lo tochlu nefesh im habasar.
Something like that.
Yes. It's a stretch. Okay. Now the גמרא Gemara goes on. Okay.
תניא נמי הכי, Tanya nami hachi, we taught similarly, I'm sorry, okay.
תניא נמי הכי Tanya nami hachi we taught similarly. אבר מן החי
נוהג בבהמה חיה ועוף. Eiver min hachai noheg b'vehema chaya v'of. אבר
מן החי eiver min hachai applies to domesticated non-domesticated and even birds.
בין טמאה בין טהורה bein tmeia bein t'hora whether kosher or non-kosher.
שנאמר רק חזק לבלתי אכול הדם, shene'emar rak chazak l'vilti achol hadam,
strengthen yourself now to eat the blood, כל שאתה מצווה. kol she'atah
mtzuvah.
if you're prohibited against the blood you're prohibited to eat the limbs
of such an animal that are torn off while alive which means
even non-kosher animals and even birds; we're prohibited about the blood of
birds. וכל שאי אתה מצווה על דמו *ve-chol she-ei atah metzuveh al
damo* if you're not prohibited against the blood like what would be
something you're not prohibited against the blood? Grasshoppers, fish; no אבר מן
החי Eiver Min Hachai *ever min hachai* by fish. Okay. וכל שאי
אתה מצווה על דמו אי אתה מצווה על אבריו *ve-chol she-ei atah
metzuveh al damo ei atah metzuveh al evarav* there's not a problem
of אבר מן החי Eiver Min Hachai? *ever min hachai*. דברי רבי
Rebbi אליעזר *divrei Rabbi Eliezer*. Now here notice it doesn't say Rabbi
Yehuda, it says Rabbi Eliezer and that's why the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara*
quoted it because otherwise it's basically the exact same line. Well that's
the thing; first of all it's telling you the דרשה *drasha*, so
that's consistent with what רבא Rava *Rava* was the one before who
said it's based on the פסוק *pasuk*, I'm sorry, רבי Rebbi, יוחנן
*Rabbi Yochanan*, and here the ברייתא braita, *braita* explicitly tells you it's
based on this פסוק *pasuk* linking it to blood, and it also
emphasizes רבי Rebbi אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer*. So Rabbi Yehuda doesn't need a
פסוק *pasuk*, he would say of course larger scope, the second one
takes effect. For Rabbi Eliezer maybe doesn't normally agree to that, but
here you've got a פסוק *pasuk* that says the same way blood
of non-kosher animals is prohibited, limbs of non-kosher animals. וחכמים אומרים *ve-chachamim
omrim* but the sages say אינו נוהג אלא בטהורים *eino noheg ela
be-tehorim* only kosher animals שנאמר *she-ne'emar* לא תאכל הנפש lo tochal hanefesh,
עם הבשר *lo tachal ha-nefesh im ha-basar* don't eat it with the
meat, meaning don't eat the meat when the life force is still
in the animal. אלא בשר basar לחוד *ela basar le-chud* you only
eat the meat when it's not with this life force in the
animal.
כל שבשרו מותר אתה מצווה על אבריו *kol she-besaro mutar atah metzuveh
al evarav*.
In a case where the meat is permissible, that's where you're prohibited
against the limbs. כל שאין בשרו מותר אין in, אתה מצווה על
אבריו *kol she-ein besaro mutar ein atah metzuveh al evarav*. When the
meat is not permitted, there's no special prohibition about the limbs, either
because of an איסור חל על איסור *issur chal al issur* problem,
or it seems like forget איסור חל על איסור *issur chal al
issur*, it's more maybe normally איסור חל על איסור *issur chal al
issur* wouldn't be an issue, it's larger scope, but it's more of
a categorical exclusion. The תורה Torah *Torah* is telling you something and
you can understand that, meaning I understand why at an emotional level
we feel אבר מן החי Eiver Min Hachai *ever min hachai* is
such an offensive thing, we'd like it to apply across the board.
Maybe we'd even like it to apply to fish for all I
know. Although remember, as I pointed out, the new sort of Japanese
cuisine is eating actual live fish. Anyway, but yeah you take these
small little live fish like minnows while they're still alive and you
swallow them whole and you feel them squiggle their way down your
throat. It's supposed to be, it's supposed to be a delicacy. What?
Apparently not. Anyway, goldfish by the way are kosher, so you technically
could do that if you have to have a college hazing הלכה
halacha ופסוק *halacha ve-psuk*. Okay, anyway, but,
but maybe we would feel that we would want that to apply.
But, but you do understand that even though that logic could apply,
what the תורה *Torah* is saying is, look, certain things are off
limits already. Non-kosher animals are off limits already, so you shouldn't be
eating them regardless. And you're not going to come to rip limbs
off of it to eat it or do other types of things
because it's already forbidden. But in the things that you are allowed
to eat, even within those there are additional restrictions. Don't eat the
גיד הנשה Gid Hanasheh, *Gid Hanasheh*, don't eat an אבר מן החי
Eiver Min Hachai, *ever min hachai*. So you understand sort of the
logic there. So it's not necessarily an איסור חל על איסור *issur
chal al issur*, but it's an issue that the prohibition is only
applies to things that otherwise you would be eating. Okay, so that
is the debate. Now the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* goes on.
Where were we? רבי Rebbi מאיר אומר *Rabbi Meir omer* now we
have a third opinion; Rabbi Meir says אינו נוהג אלא בבהמה טהורה
Tehora, בלבד *eino noheg ela be-vehema tehora bilvad*. He excludes not only,
not only non-kosher animals, but even birds and חיה *chaya*, even a
deer. Okay, it's not an אבר מן החי Eiver Min Hachai *ever
min hachai*. And we're going to see there's not a particular like,
you know, conceptual or philosophical reason, but it's based on the verse.
אמר רבה בר שמואל אמר רב Amar Rav, חסדא ואיתימא *Amar Rabbah
bar Shmuel amar Rav Chisda ve-iteima* so now there's going to be
a whole different version of who said the following thing. So one
is רבה בר שמואל *Rabbah bar Shmuel* in the name of רב
Rav חסדא *Rav Chisda* ואיתימא *ve-iteima* רב Rav יוסף *Rav Yosef*, and
maybe רב Rav יוסף *Rav Yosef*; so that's one tradition. ואמרי לה
*ve-amrei lah* and some say אמר רבה בר שילא אמר רב Amar
Rav חסדא ואיתימא רב Rav יוסף *amar Rabbah bar Shila amar Rav
Chisda ve-iteima Rav Yosef* so that the, it wasn't רבה בר שמואל
*Rabbah bar Shmuel* saying it in the name of one of these
two rabbis, it was רבה בר שילא *Rabbah bar Shila*. ואמרי לה
*ve-amrei lah* and some say רבה בר שימי אמר רב Amar Rav,
חסדא ואיתימא רב יוסף *Rabbah bar Shimi amar Rav Chisda ve-iteima Rav
Yosef*; three different versions of the two possibilities of who said it
in the name of two possible people. Anyway, מאי טעמא Mai taama,
דרבי מאיר *Mai ta'ama de-Rabbi Meir*? What's the reason of Rabbi Meir?
אמר קרא *amar kra* the verse says וזבחת מבקרך ומצאנך *ve-zavachta mi-be-karecha
u-mi-tzoncha*. It says if you slaughter from your cattle or your sheep
don't eat the blood and don't eat the soul with the meat.
So the whole thing that introduces this is about cattle and sheep.
So therefore it is limited to בהמה *behema*, not חיה *chaya* and
עוף Of *of*. Although of course you would not know, maybe anyway,
of course he would of course not disagree that the prohibition of
blood applies to birds and חיה *chaya*, but that we know elsewhere.
Since this is the source of אבר מן החי Eiver Min Hachai.
*ever min hachai* and we don't know the prohibition of birds there,
this is limited to the case of it says in the introduction
of the verse, which is cattle and sheep. Okay, those are the
debate of the scope of אבר מן החי Eiver Min Hachai, *ever
min hachai*. So since we talked about גיד gid. הנשה *Gid Hanasheh*
scope, we're talking about אבר מן החי Eiver Min Hachai *ever min
hachai* scope. אמר רב גידל אמר רב Amar Rav Gidel amar Rav.
*Amar Rav Gidel amar Rav* now by the way it's not my
theory here although of course it makes total sense that the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* is talking about it here because it is very similar
discussions as is it חל איסור, is it fundamentally excluded from non-kosher
animals? But it's also, this is the מסכת Masechet that is devoted
to eating meat. And the interesting thing is is that there are
some basic discussions that are left out of the משניות. Mishnayot. And
the גמרא, Gemara I, my theory is, has to find a way
to get them into the discussion. So the משניות Mishnayot talk about
גיד הנשה, they talk about בשר בחלב, Basar Bechalav, what they don't
talk about is דם, Dam, removing the blood, they don't talk about
חלב. Chelev. Now the משנה Mishna alluded to חלב Chelev because the
משנה Mishna said can you trust the butchers to remove the חלב
Chelev or not? But the גמרא, Gemara if you remember, the גמרא
Gemara has found ways to have large discussions about which parts of
the חלב Chelev are prohibited or not. So similar if we're talking
about eating meat, the גמרא's Gemara. going to make sure to discuss
whether you can eat אבר מן החי Eiver Min Hachai or you
can't, but what are the parameters of אבר מן החי? Eiver Min
Hachai So it's good getting all the relevant topics into the conversation.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara, continues. Okay. אמר רב, Amar Rav,
אמר רב Amar Rav, גידל אמר רב. So says Rav Gidel says
Rav, line starting with the word אמר רב about 20 lines from
the bottom. מחלוקת בישראל. Machloket BeYisrael. This whole debate about whether אבר
מן החי Eiver Min Hachai applies to non-kosher animals is by Jews,
here you go, Rivka. אבל בבני נח, Aval BeVnei Noach, by non-Jews,
דברי הכל מוזהר לטמאים כטהורים. divrei hakol muzar le-tme'im ke-tehorim. Of course
it applies to non-kosher animals. Why shouldn't it? All the issues of
איסור חל איסור issur chal issur are not relevant because they're not
prohibited to them. And the fact that if you say a verse
says 'oh, it only applies to animals you could otherwise eat' fine,
they could otherwise eat this animal! So there's no reason to not,
and it does apply to non-kosher animals. Okay now, of course, okay
now the question of course that Rivka asks, which is how can
they be more prohibited than Jews? The גמרא Gemara is not bothered
with that because the basic answer is is that they're not more
prohibited. Non-kosher animals are already prohibited to Jews. And אבר מן החי,
Eiver Min Hachai you know, an אבר מן החי Eiver Min Hachai,
of a camel is equally prohibited to a Jew and a non,
to a Jew because it's camel and to the non-Jew because it's
אבר מן החי. eiver min hachai. תניא נמי הכי, Tanya nami hachi,
we taught similarly, one minute. אבר
מן החי, eiver min hachai here's the ברייתא, braita אבר מן החי
eiver min hachai? בן נח מוזהר לו, Ben Noach muzar lo, a
בן נח Ben Noach is
prohibited against אבר מן החי eiver min hachai. על הטמאים כטהורים, al
hatme'im ketehorim, by non-kosher animals just as equally as to kosher animals.
וישראל אינו מוזהר אלא על הטהורין בלבד. VeYisrael eino muzar ela al
hatehorin bilvad. And a Jew is only by kosher animals, like the
opinion of the חכמים. Chakhamim. איכא דאמרי, Ika de'amri, now some say
the גרסא girsa of this ברייתא braita was טהורה, only by kosher
animal, like in the singular. ורבי מאיר היא, VeRabbi Meir hi, and
it's Rabbi Meir, meaning one species of kosher animal, meaning the domesticated
one, so it's in the singular. איכא דאמרי טהורין, Ika de'amri Tehorim,
kosher animals, ורבנן היא, VeRabbanan hi, and it's the Rabbis who say
it's a wide group of kosher animals... excuse me, not non-kosher, kosher
animals. So it says Jews are only prohibited on kosher. So is
it kosher ones or kosher ones? So according to Rabbi Meir it's
kosher ones because it's basically kosher cattle and sheep, you know, could
have domesticated, but according to the חכמים Chakhamim it's kosher ones, any
kosher animals: birds, cattle, sheep, deer. But Jews are only kosher, non-Jews
אבר מן החי eiver min hachai apply even to non-kosher. You had
a question?
My question is, you know, Rabbi Meir seems to be citing a
very good point, דברה תורה כצאן ובבקר. dibra hatorah ketzon uvabakar. So
what do the חכמים Chakhamim do about that?
Well, they just say the דם, Dam, the דם Dam obviously means
that it's not דוקא. davka. דברה תורה בהוה, Dibra hatorah bahoveh, you
know, because the prohibition of דם Dam is not limited to that.
Okay, now we go on. אמר רב שיזבי, Amar Rav Shizbi, אף
אנן נמי תנינא, af anan nami tanina, we taught similarly in a
משנה. Mishna. אכל אבר מן החי. Achal Eiver Min Hachai. Now this
is talking
about a kosher bird. Okay,
the משנה Mishna that talks about the status of kosher birds, non-kosher
birds for בני נח, Bnei Noach, for בני ישראל. Bnei Yisrael. So
here it says אכל אבר מן החי. Achal Eiver Min Hachai. Just
let me, I just want to check רש״י Rashi here a second.
I'm sorry, non-kosher bird, not kosher, non-kosher bird. So here it's talking
about non-kosher bird. If you ate an אבר מן החי eiver min
hachai ממנה, mimena, from it...
רש״י Rashi is bothered by the way, I'm sure everybody's about to
ask me this question why it says ממנה mimena the feminine since
עוף is masculine and it should have been ממנו. mimenu. Anyway, so
רש״י Rashi points out because earlier in the ברייתא baraita it had
been referring to a נבילה, Nevela, which is a feminine, so it's
keeping the feminized form here of the noun. Anyway, אכל אבר מן
החי Achal Eiver Min Hachai ממנה, mimena, if somebody ate an אבר
מן החי eiver min hachai from a non-kosher bird, אינו סופג ארבעים,
eino sofeg arba'im, you don't get forty lashes. Now that's of course
a little bit of a problem. We understand that you might not
transgress for אבר מן החי, eiver min hachai that was our earlier
discussion, but why don't you transgress for eating a non-kosher bird? Right?
So we'll get back to that in a minute, let's just bracket
that for now. ואין שחיטתה מטהרתה, Ve'ein shechitata metaherata, and shechting it
does not make it either טהור tahor or kosher. טהור Tahor could
mean either kosher or טהור. tahor. We will see that this is
a question in a minute in the גמרא. Gemara במאי, Bimai, now
what do we talking about says the גמרא, Gemara that's the end
of the משנה. Mishna. אילימא בישראל, Ileima beYisrael, if we're talking about
a Jew, פשיטא דאין שחיטתה מטהרתה. pshita de'ein shechitata metaherata. So obviously
if you shecht a non-kosher bird it's not going to become kosher.
And what's the alternative explanation? נבילה. Nevela. The alternative explanation is whether
it creates טומאת נבילה. tumat nevela. Okay, but the problem there is,
and the reason the גמרא Gemara doesn't go for that explanation, is
because even if a non-kosher bird were to die naturally Normally it
would not have טומאת נבילה.
tumas
neveilah.
Okay, טומאת נבילה tumas neveilah is only by like mammals. Birds, the
only טומאה tumah of a bird as a dead bird, real טומאה-טומאה,
is a kosher bird that's a נבילה neveilah and only when you
swallow it. So very bizarre the טומאה tumah of birds and it's
only kosher נבילות neveilos and only when swallowed. So since this says
your שחיטה shechitah doesn't get it out of טומאה, tumah, טומאה tumah
can't mean טומאה tumah, here if we're talking about non-kosher birds. So
it has to mean doesn't make it kosher. But of course שחיטה
shechitah doesn't make it kosher; it's a non-kosher bird! So we can't
be talking about Jews.
So where were we? ואין שחיטתה מטהרתה במה? v'ein shechitasah meta-har-sah bemah?
Even by a Jew? פשיטא דאין שחיטתה מטהרתה. pshita de'ein shechitasah meta-har-sah.
אלא בבני נח. ella biBnei Noach. We must be talking about בני
נח. Bnei Noach. So what does it mean by בני נח? Bnei
Noach? You've got a non-kosher bird; they're allowed to eat it, but
what can't they eat? They can't eat an אבר מן החי. eiver
min hachai The שחיטה shechitah doesn't solve the problem. Why does שחיטה
shechitah not solve the problem? So because for a Jew, at what
stage... no, no, no, at what stage if you שחט shecht an
animal and the animal was still flopping around, which animals will do
after שחט-ed, shecht at what stage does it stop being אבר מן
החי eiver min hachai for a Jew?
The moment you
שחט, shecht, then it's considered to be dead or permissible to be
eaten. For a בן נח, Ben Noach, if you שחט shecht an
animal and it's still flopping around, when does it stop being אבר
מן החי? eiver min hachai Only when it stops moving, when it's
considered to be biologically, physically dead. Now, interestingly though, if you שחט
shecht a...
what's if you שחט shecht a kosher
animal? Now I've got this kosher cow or chicken flopping around; for
a Jew I can take a piece of meat and eat it,
it's not אבר מן החי. eiver min hachai Is a בן נח
Ben Noach prohibited? Because for him maybe it's not considered dead. There
are some that say a בן נח Ben Noach is prohibited. But
that then gets to our logical problem: Is there can there be
something that a בן נח Ben Noach is prohibited for that a
Jew is not? So therefore there's other opinions that say since normally
what we say as a result of that question that means that
we're going to make it forbidden even for a Jew, but sometimes
we go the opposite way. We say we'll say that it's permitted
for a בן נח, Ben Noach, and that's what some say here.
That if you שחט shecht a chicken and it's still flopping around,
the same way a Jew can now eat it, a בן נח
Ben Noach can also now eat it. Even for a בן נח
Ben Noach it's not אבר מן החי eiver min hachai since this
is permissible to be eaten at this stage for Jews. That's for
kosher animals. Let's say I didn't שחט shecht a chicken. Let's say
instead I שחט-ed shecht my-my friend the camel that we like talking
about, okay, and that's flopping around. Can a בן נח Ben Noach
eat it now after it's been שחט-ed? shecht The answer is no,
because a Jew can't eat it. So therefore, that's now what we're
saying this משנה Mishnah means. You have your non-kosher bird, שחט-ing shecht
that, as opposed to שחט-ing shecht your chicken, here you're שחט-ing shecht
your I don't know, what are you שחט-ing, shecht your ostrich? Okay,
so שחט-ing shecht your ostrich, the שחיטה shechitah does make it permitted
to the בן נח. Ben Noach. As soon as it's שחט-ed, shecht
even if it's flopping around? Let's say whatever. But שחט-ing shecht your
ostrich, the שחיטה shechitah does not make it permitted to the בן
נח Ben Noach until it actually dies. So that's how we're reading
that משנה: Mishnah: אין שחיטתה מטהרתה. ein shechitasah meta-har-sah. The שחיטה shechitah
does not make it permitted. If it's talking about טומאה, tumah it's
not טמא tamei anyway. If it's talking about כשרות, kashrus, of course
שחיטה shechitah doesn't make it permitted to the Jew; it's a non-kosher
bird, nothing makes it permitted to the Jew. The only way to
read that phrase is: It's a non-kosher bird for a בן נח
Ben Noach and the only question was אבר מן החי Ever Min
HaChai and we're saying שחט-ing shecht it does not get it out
of אבר מן החי Ever Min HaChai as long as it's flopping
around, although it would for a chicken because that's permissible to Jews.
For a non-kosher bird, for the ostrich, שחיטה shechitah does not get
it out of the אבר מן החי Ever Min HaChai category. I'll
take your questions in a minute, let's just finish why the גמרא
Gemara is making this point. אלא לאו בבני נח מכלל דאסור, ella
lav biBnei Noach michlal de'assur, which from there we can infer, ah,
that proves it! Since the only way to read this משנה Mishnah
was שחט-ing shecht an ostrich and can the בן נח Ben Noach
eat it while it's still flopping around, you see that בני נח
Bnei Noach are prohibited in אבר מן החי Ever Min HaChai on
non-kosher animals. That was all the reason we quoted it, to prove
that although Jews' אבר מן החי Ever Min HaChai does not apply
to non-kosher animals, for בני נח Bnei Noach it even applies, which
is of course logically of course, why shouldn't it? No איסור כולל,
issur kolel, no other reason, but now it's just showing it, that
this משנה Mishnah is talking about non-kosher birds and we're saying that
the אבר מן החי Ever Min HaChai remains a problem even after
שחט-ed shecht and therefore you see that אבר מן החי Ever Min
HaChai is a problem in non-kosher animals at least for בני נח.
Bnei Noach. Question?
You mean בני נח Bnei Noach get מלקות ארבעים? malkos arba'im? Where
do we see that?
No, whatever בני נח Bnei Noach get.
It says אינו סופג את הארבעים. eino sofeg es ha'arba'im.
Oh, that's going to be talking about Jews. We'll get back to
that in a minute. Yes?
Is this formal or technical, meaning are we saying that formalistically we
have to say that a בן נח Ben Noach is also prohibited
from the אבר מן החי Ever Min HaChai from שחיטה shechitah of
kosher animals or are we saying that technically שחיטה shechitah is the
point of death for kosher animals and it's not the point of
death for non-kosher animals?
I believe the latter. I didn't get the former. Tell me the
former?
The former is yes really שחיטה Shechita is not actually the point
of death, שחיטה Shechita is a מתיר Matir that works for both
for all animals?
Oh, yeah I think both yeah that's an excellent question and yeah
both are serious possibilities. We talked about that. We talked about that
a while ago. Okay. Anyway, now Michael has a very reasonable question
which is the beginning of the משנה Mishnah speaks about getting lashes,
that's not a concept by בני נח. Bnei Noach. More than that,
forget that, the beginning of the משנה Mishnah says you don't get
lashes for אבר מן החי Ever Min HaChai from a non-kosher bird
and here we just said the end of the משנה Mishnah was
saying that אבר מן החי Ever Min HaChai does apply to non-kosher
birds for בני נח. Bnei Noach. So what do you do? The
beginning of the משנה Mishnah says it doesn't apply to non-kosher birds
and now you read the end of the משנה Mishnah to say
it does apply to non-kosher birds, make up your mind. So that's
what the גמרא Gemara gets to. So the גמרא Gemara says רב
מני בר פטיש רמי רישא סיפא. Rav Mani bar Patish rami reisha
seifa. So רב מני בר פטיש Rav Mani bar Patish shows the
contradiction of the beginning and the end. ומשני, Umeshani, the גמרא Gemara
doesn't even have to spell it out, it's so obvious the problem.
ומשני, Umeshani, he answers רישא בישראל וסיפא בבני נח, reisha b'Yisrael v'seifa
b'Bnei Noach, which is not the most satisfying answer but that's what
we have to say. The first part that talked about lashes as
Michael pointed out is only a concept by Jews and there it
says אבר מן החי Ever Min HaChai by non-kosher birds does not
apply to Jews, it only applies by kosher animals, but the end
is talking about non-Jews and for them אבר מן החי Ever Min
HaChai, does apply and שחיטה Shechita doesn't get it out of the
category actually half the time. What? Yeah. אמר רב, so moving on
now, now we have put aside the question about אבר מן החי
Ever Min HaChai for non-kosher animals and now we get to the
question about the שיעור shiur and the difference between אבר מן החי
Ever Min HaChai and בשר מן החי. Basar Min HaChai. How much
of an אבר ever do you have to eat to transgress? Let's
take a look. אמר רב, אבר מן החי צריך כזית. Ever Min
HaChai tzarich kezayis. You have to eat a כזית kezayis of it
like all other forbidden foods. מאי טעמא, אכילה כתיבא בה. achila kesiva
bah. It says לא תאכל, lo tochal, eating means a כזית. kezayis.
So מתיב רב עמרם, masiv Rav Amram, so רב עמרם Rav Amram
asks on this a ברייתא baraita that kind of seems to contradict
it, this is not a ברייתא משנה, mishnah, the משנה mishnah we
just had a minute ago. אכל אבר מן החי הימנה אינו סופג
את הארבעים ואין שחיטה מטהרתה. Achal Ever Min HaChai mimena eino soveg
es ha'arbaim v'ein shechitah m'taharasa. Okay now we just said that was
the משנה mishnah we just said. Now there forget the end which
was the complicated part, the first part says if a Jew eats
an אבר מן החי Ever Min HaChai from a non-kosher bird you
don't get lashes. So the question is, okay I understand you don't
get lashes for אבר מן החי Ever Min HaChai but why not
get lashes for eating ostrich, right? ואי סלקא דעתך בעינן כזית, Ve'isalka
daatach be'inan kezayis, so he says and if you think that you
will only be talking when you're eating an אבר מן החי Ever
Min HaChai that you ate a כזית kezayis worth, תיפוק ליה דאכל
כזית, teipok lei d'achal kezayis, so if the scenario is when it
says you don't get lashes for אבר מן החי ever min hachay
from ostrich, what does it mean? According to you it means you
ate a כזית kezayis of אבר מן החי ever min hachay. of
ostrich and you don't get lashes. So he says alright you don't
get lashes for אבר מן החי, ever min hachay get lashes for
ostrich. Now I would understand it because I would say you don't
need a כזית kezayis for אבר מן החי ever min hachay you
basically just need the whole limb. Remember the concept of בריה, biryah,
an entire entity? So let's say you eat the whole limb, so
let's take a small limb, I don't know what a small limb
of a bird would be, do I get something that has maybe
a finger? Birds don't have they have claws, right? So let's say
you ate I guess the claw, okay, so whatever that wouldn't be
a כזית, kezayis, so now it's saying if you ate that limb
you don't get lashes for אבר מן החי ever min hachay, you
also don't get lashes for ostrich because it wasn't a כזית kezayis
there. So for me it makes sense, but if you say you
have to eat a כזית kezayis of the אבר מן החי ever
min hachay why do you not get lashes you ate a כזית
kezayis of ostrich? So the גמרא Gemara says you like my example
my example for non-kosher animals, camels and ostrich. So anyway גמרא Gemara
says ואי סלקא דעתך תיפוק ליה דאכל כזית. ve'isalka daatach teipok lei
d'achal kezayis. So גמרא Gemara says כדיאמר רב נחמן. k'de'amar Rav Nachman.
So רב נחמן Rav Nachman explains this in another context in a
similar question, במה
שהוא בשר גידים ועצמות. b'ma shehu basar gidim v'atzamot. There's only a
little bit of בשר basar but there's a lot of גידים gidim
and עצמות. atzamot. So you can have you have to eat a
כזית kezayis of the limb but the limb it's different than the
meat, right? The בשר basar, is the בשר, the limb can include
the bones that are part of the limb. So therefore here's what
he is saying, what's my scenario? You ate a limb of ostrich,
okay, and you don't get lashes for אבר מן החי ever min
hachay but it was a כזית. kezayis. Why was it a כזית?
kezayis? Because it had a half a כזית kezayis of meat and
a half a כזית kezayis of bone. So it was a limb
that had the whole thing was a כזית. kezayis. Why don't you
get lashes for eating ostrich? Because you didn't eat a כזית kezayis
of meat. For the prohibition of eating ostrich you have to eat
the meat of the ostrich. For the prohibition of eating the limb
then it can it also includes the bones that are part of
that limb. So therefore you can transgress אבר מן החי ever min
hachay without eating a כזית kezayis of meat, you need a כזית
kezayis of אבר ever but not a כזית kezayis of meat. Yeah.
שיעור Shiur why don't we say exactly that it's a בריה?
biryah? בריה, Biryah, so the גמרא Gemara does not directly discuss why
it's not בריה, biryah, the presumably one simple answer is that according
to one explanation of תוספות Tosafot that בריה biryah is when the
תורה explicitly labels the thing not to eat, like don't eat a
שרץ, sheretz, so you eat a whole שרץ, sheretz, don't eat a
גיד. Here it didn't exactly say don't eat an אבר, ever, I
mean it sort of we say it means an אבר ever but
it says לא תאכל הנפש, so therefore since it doesn't identify it
as a unit, it's therefore even it wouldn't have a דין din
בריה. biryah. But yes this is a question do you in general
hold of בריה biryah and what constitutes בריה? biryah? Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara goes on, so הכא נמי hacha nami here too.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara goes on. הכא נמי Hacha nami
here too במשהו בשר גידים והעצמות, be-mashu basar gidim ve-ha'atzamot, it's only
a little bit of meat and the bones fill in the rest.
תא שמע, Ta shema, so we're still going to try to figure
this out, come and hear, דאמר רב, de-amar Rav, as said that
רב said, אכל ציפור טהורה בחייה בכל שהוא. achal tzipor tehora be-chayeha
be-chol shehu. Let's say you take a kosher bird. What's a small
kosher bird? A sparrow? Hummingbird? That's not kosher. Okay. What? Quail is
kosher, smaller than a sparrow? Okay. You take a sparrow, okay, and
you ate it up, and you ate it. Now,
okay, now, so
אכל ציפור טהורה בחייה, achal tzipor tehora be-chayeha, you ate it whole
basically, okay, so if you ate it when it was alive, then
you transgress even or you ate a part of it or whatever,
anyway, you transgress בכל שהוא be-chol shehu even the smallest amount. ובמיתתה
U-ve-mitata if it's dead, then it's not an אבר מן החי ever
min hachai, problem, it's a נבילה neveila problem, so as a נבילה
neveila בכזית. be-kezayit.
So a נבילה neveila everybody agrees requires a כזית kezayit to transgress.
וטמאה, U-tmeia, if it's a non-kosher animal, בין בחייה בין במיתתה בכל
שהוא, bein be-chayeha bein be-mitata be-chol shehu, whether alive or dead, it's
the smallest amount. Why? Because a non-kosher animal, if you eat a
whole non-kosher bird, okay, so a whole bird, you are transgressing for
eating a non-kosher bird and that's the בריה birya issue. Okay, so
let me just take a step back and explain what he says.
You've eaten a whole bird, all right, somehow you swallowed a whole
bird. Kosher or non-kosher? We'll talk. Okay, if it's kosher and alive,
so what you've done is you've eaten an אבר מן החי. ever
min hachai, So an אבר מן החי ever min hachai. this he's
assuming you don't need a כזית, kezayit, an אבר ever is enough,
so certainly if an אבר ever is enough, a whole bird is
enough. Okay, then you transgress. Even אבר, ever, right? אבר. Ever.
Yeah. We'll talk about, you didn't cut it up into the אברים,
evarim, whatever, we won't worry about that right now. You've transgressed, you've
eaten a whole thing. Okay, if it's dead, then even if you've
eaten the whole thing, נבילה neveila does not, the whole thing isn't
relevant. By נבילה neveila the amount is a כזית kezayit because נבילה
neveila never the Torah never identifies like what type of item, it
doesn't say don't eat a cow, a dead cow, it says don't
eat the meat of a נבילה, neveila, so therefore it's always goes
by a כזית. kezayit. But if it's talking about אבר, ever, אבר
ever is a unit, you ate the whole unit, even less than
a כזית. kezayit. When it is a non-kosher bird, the Torah says
don't eat non-kosher birds. So therefore as a unit it's significant. So
whether alive or dead, alive as an אבר מן החי ever min
hachai or alive as a non-kosher bird or dead, it's
as a non-kosher bird, it's prohibited even when it is less than
a כזית. kezayit. Somehow I feel that I wasn't making that clear.
Let me try one last time and then we'll move on.
The idea of בריה birya when there's a unit significant to some
degree depends on when the Torah identifies the unit as being what
is problematic. So when it says don't eat non-kosher animals, the whole
animal is explicitly being said don't eat this animal. So therefore if
you ate the whole animal, like a whole ant or a whole
tiny bird that was less than a כזית, kezayit, even if it
was less than a כזית kezayit you ate the whole thing. Don't
eat an אבר מן החי, ever min hachai if you ate the
whole אבר, ever, even less than a כזית kezayit you transgress. When
it says don't eat נבילה, neveila, נבילה neveila just really refers to
the meat, not to a particular unit. There you need a כזית.
kezayit. So that's what this thing is saying. It's saying that you
ate a whole bird. If it's an אבר מן החי ever min
hachai. alive, you transgress even less than a כזית. kezayit. If it's
dead, it's נבילה, neveila, you need a כזית. kezayit. If it's a
non-kosher bird, you transgress because it's a non-kosher bird. Non-kosher bird it's
a whole unit, so therefore you also transgress even less than a
כזית. kezayit. The פשט pshat being that אבר מן החי ever min
hachai, did not need a כזית, kezayit, the whole unit even less
than a כזית kezayit you transgress.
Can we say second? No questions.
No questions now Michael. We just have very little time and people
have to stay focused. Okay. So, so the גמרא Gemara says, so
you see there even if it's not a כזית, kezayit, if it's
a whole unit that's enough. So the גמרא Gemara. says, הכא נמי,
Hacha nami, here too במשהו בשר, be-mashu basar, it's a little bit
of meat but גידים והעצמות gidim ve-ha'atzamot but the limbs complete, but
the bones complete the amount. So רב is saying that there really
is a כזית, kezayit, which is really not the simple sense, because
רב is saying you eat the whole unit even less than a
כזית. kezayit. But he's saying oh we don't really mean less than
a כזית, kezayit, we really mean that there's a כזית kezayit of
everything combined, it just means that there's not a כזית kezayit of
meat. But that's not the same as the end, because when you
eat the non-kosher bird, even if there's less than a כזית kezayit
of the whole thing, like you eat an ant, no matter how
small the animal is, if you eat the whole non-kosher ant, you
transgress. So the end of the משנה Mishna certainly means that there's
not a כזית kezayit amongst the whole thing, but here we're trying
to reinterpret it to say, oh no no no for אבר מן
החי ever min hachai. you do need a כזית, kezayit, all he's
saying is you didn't need a כזית kezayit of meat, but you
did have a כזית kezayit of the whole limb combined.
For kosher bird. For kosher, right, and
non-kosher even less than that.
Right, because of non-kosher animals, correct.
Everyone agrees to that, and that's what we said before. Yeah.
תא שמע, Ta shema, come and hear. נטל ציפור שאין בו כזית
ואכלו. natal tzipor she-ein bo kezayit ve-achalo.
So you took a bird that does not have a כזית kezayit
in the entire bird and you ate it. Okay, same type of
story.
One minute.
Okay. So you took a bird that does not have a כזית
kezayit and you ate it. רבי פוטר, Rebbi poter, רבי says you're
exempt. רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון מחייב. Rebbi Elazar be-Rebbi Shimon mechayev. And
רבי אלעזר Rebbi Elazar son of רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon says you're
חייב. chayav. Now what are they debating? So it seems like this
is, maybe they're debating the issue about do you transgress for less
than a כזית? kzayis? You ate this whole bird, whole, alive, which
basically is a prohibition of אבר מן החי, eiver min hachai. but
it doesn't have a כזית, kzayis, let's say kosher. So אמר רבי
אלעזר בר רבי שמעון, Amar Rebbe Elazar bar Rebbe Shimon, so let's
see what they're debating. קל וחומר, Kal vachomer, here's a קל וחומר
kal vachomer why I should say that you should transgress. על אבר
ממנה חי, על כולה לא כל שכן? Al ever mimena chay, al
kula lo kol shekein? If you transgress for even a limb, you
should certainly transgress for eating the whole thing. So presumably that's their
debate. Presumably what Rebbe is saying is, you know why you don't
transgress in this case?
Because it's not a limb, it's the whole bird. The prohibition is
to rip a limb, take a limb that is ripped from a
living animal and eat it, not to eat an entire animal.
So the גמרא Gemara says
like חנקה ואכלה, chanka ve’achala, if you choked it and ate it,
so then it would basically be a נבילה. neveilah. So then דברי
הכל בכזית, divrei hakol bikzayis, everybody would say again, a נבילה neveilah
you do not transgress by eating the whole thing, a נבילה neveilah
everybody agrees, since it's about amount of stuff, not about a unit,
that you need a כזית. kzayis. In a בריה? biryah?
What? בריה? Biryah? I'm trying to understand, is it בריה? biryah? According
to בריה, biryah, yeah, whatever, the בריה biryah doesn't apply if you
ate a whole ציפור tzippor you're not חייב chayav if it's less
than כזית kzayis despite the fact that it's a בריה? biryah?
If you ate the whole ציפור. tzippor.
According to Rebbe?
According to Rebbe you're not חייב. chayav.
But why isn't it a בריה biryah problem?
Well, forget that, that's what the גמרא Gemara is going to say.
But the reason is because it's not an אבר. ever. He says
you only transgress on a limb removed from an animal. It's clear
by רבי אלעזר בר רבי שמעון Rebbe Elazar bar Rebbe Shimon's response.
רבי אלעזר בר רבי שמעון Rebbe Elazar bar Rebbe Shimon's response is:
Give me a break! If you transgress on the limb, you certainly
transgress on the whole thing. And Rebbe says, presumably says, no, the
prohibition is a limb that has been removed from the animal during
the animal's life. Eating a whole living animal, you are not transgressing.
Well, that's a question. רש"י Rashi wants to say that you are
transgressing בשר מן החי, basar min hachai, not אבר ever מן החי,
but it's בשר מן החי. basar min hachai. But we're going to
bracket that for now.
Let's not get distracted by that. So let's take a look at
the גמרא. Gemara עד כאן לא פליגי Ad kan lo pligi until
now they have not debated, they're only debating אלא דמר סבר בחיי
איברים עומדת ומר סבר בחיי לאו איברים עומדת. ella de-mar savar bechayei
evarim omedet, u-mar savar bechayei lav evarim omedet. They're debating whether when
an animal is still alive, do you see an animal as already
cut up into its appropriate limbs. And there's I think there's like
a Far Side cartoon that I can't exactly remember that somehow is
like this, you know, but you see the cow walking around and
you see it all cut up like by the butcher's design, like
somebody looking at it as just meat waiting to be had. So
anyway, the question is, is that if you look at an animal
already alive as like it's just a collection of limbs, so then
when I eat it, I've eaten אבר ever מן החי. However, if
you look at it when it's alive as no, it's a living
breathing thing, I'm not looking at it as limbs, I'm looking at
it as a cow. So then when I eat it, or the
bird, so when I eat it you can't say that I've eaten
an אבר ever because we don't yet label it איברים evarim until
they are removed. That's how the גמרא Gemara frames the debate. You
could have gone further, you could say even if I look at
it as limbs, I still define אבר eiver, מן החי as a
limb removed from the animal. All right, that's true, but anyway, that's
how the גמרא gemara frames the debate. So the debate is, while
it's still alive, do you look at it as a collection of
limbs already? So that's the only reason Rebbe says you're exempt, is
because it's not a limb, it's a whole thing.
But דכולי עלמא מיהא de-kulei alma mi-ha everybody nevertheless agrees, לא בעינן
כזית. lo ba’inan kzayis. You don't need a כזית, kzayis, right, that
was the case. You ate this whole bird that didn't have a
כזית, kzayis, Rebbe says you get off because you didn't eat a
limb, and everybody else says no, certainly if by limbs you're חייב,
chayav, certainly by the whole thing. But nobody is bothered by the
fact that it's not a כזית. kzayis. You know why? Because you
ate the whole thing. So you see eating the whole thing is
enough for אבר eiver. מן החי even though it doesn't have a
כזית. kzayis. So that seems a pretty good proof.
What about if it's not slaughtered? Isn't that...
well, that's the point. Not slaughtered is a problem. It's not a
נבילה neveilah because נבילה neveilah means dead without being slaughtered. So not
slaughtered puts you in the category of אבר eiver מן החי. But
Rebbe has a, this is a loophole, because it's not a limb.
Now רש"י Rashi says it would still be בשר מן החי, basar
min hachai, but תוספות Tosafot has a whole discussion about that. For
that you would need a כזית. kzayis. Like that's why רש"י Rashi
says you'd still get off, because you don't have a כזית kzayis
of meat. For בשר מן החי basar min hachai you need a
כזית. kzayis. Anyway, so the גמרא gemara says, so here it's pretty
clear that everybody says you don't need a כזית. kzayis. So once
again we have the answer we've been reusing. And here is where
רב נחמן Rav Nachman originally said it. אמר רב נחמן Amar Rav
Nachman says רב נחמן, Rav Nachman, במשהו בשר. bemashu basar. No, it's
only a little bit of meat. The meat isn't a כזית, kzayis,
but גידים ועצמות, gidim va’atzamot, but then you also have the sinews
and the bones. So when we said there's not a כזית, kzayis,
we didn't really mean it. Really the whole bird does have a
כזית. kzayis. We just meant there's not a כזית kzayis of meat.
Because if there were a כזית kzayis of meat, then says רש"י,
Rashi, then Rebbe would agree, because then you would get transgressed for
בשר מן החי. basar min hachai. So again it's a stretch. The
simple sense of all of these proofs are that אבר מן החי,
אבר is considered a whole unit, and you will transgress by eating
the whole אבר or the whole bird certainly, according to רבי אלעזר
בר רבי שמעון, Rebbe Elazar bar Rebbe Shimon, even without eating a
כזית. kzayis. But there is an opinion that you do need a
כזית kzayis even by אבר מן החי. Now the גמרא gemara sort
of just tries to figure out the
מציאות. metzius. And the entire bird, you don't have a כזית kezayis
of meat? Right, that's what we said the scenario was. You swallowed
the whole bird and we're saying that not only that the whole
bird is tiny and isn't a כזית, kezayis, that we could imagine,
but now we're saying that the bird is, the bird is a
כזית kezayis big, but there's not a כזית kezayis of meat on
it. Okay, so there's not a כזית kezayis of meat on the
bird and more than that,
ובחד אבר אית כזית uve'chad eiver is kezayis basar. But and since
it says that we would agree that you would transgress if you
ate a limb, so and according to this opinion you only transgress
if you eat a כזית, kezayis, that means we're describing a bird
that one of its limbs is already a כזית. kezayis. So that's
a significant size and in the entire bird there's not a כזית
kezayis of meat. Okay, you see how we said that? Since it
says everybody would agree that if you ate a limb, presumably you
tore a limb off, you would transgress and we're saying that a
limb has to be, you have to eat a כזית-worth kezayis according
to this approach, right, then it means that even one limb has
a כזית. kezayis. We're also saying what does it mean when it
says that you didn't eat a כזית? kezayis? It means you didn't
have a כזית kezayis of meat on the entire bird. So you've
got a bird that you can't say the bird is tiny because
even one of its one limb is a כזית kezayis and nevertheless
on the entire bird you don't have a כזית kezayis of meat.
That's a pretty bony thin bird. So can such a thing exist?
So the גמרא gemara says,
אמר רב שביא, Amar Rav Shiviya, אין, yes,
בקלוניתא, be'kalanisa,
there's this bird a קלוניתא kalanisa that is exactly like that. That
is a very bony bird and very tiny and doesn't have a
כזית kezayis of meat but one limb is a כזית. kezayis. I
have no idea what it is. I am sure the ArtScroll does
not translate it. Does the ArtScroll, though, does Steinsaltz suggest what a
קלוניתא kalanisa is?
There's
several opinions.
Let's find some. Several bony thin small birds.
Part of my confusion, I mean, we're talking about טמא tamei or
טהור tahor because, well,
that's what we're going to say in a second. טהור. tahor.
Maybe it's some kind of a sea bird which was very skinny
and its meat is not very suitable for eating.
All right, whatever, moving on. קלוניתא. kalanisa. All right, so גמרא gemara
says,
אמר רב שביא, Amar Rav Shiviya, oh, גמרא gemara, says אימא סיפא,
eima seifa, look at the end, חנקה ואכלה דברי הכל בכזית. chinka
ve'achla divrei hakol bekezayis. If it died, then it's a נבלה, neveilah,
everybody agrees you need a כזית. kezayis. והא קלוניתא עוף טמא הוא.
ve'ha'kalanisa uf tamei hu. But a קלוניתא kalanisa is a non-kosher bird,
and as a non-kosher bird you eat, everybody agrees you transgress if
you eat the whole bird, right? The whole discussion of whether you
transgress if you eat a whole limb, but if you eat a
whole non-kosher bird, whole non-kosher ant, or whatever, whole ant, everybody agrees
that that you transgress. So here if you need a כזית, kezayis,
we're not talking about, we're talking about kosher birds, not non-kosher birds.
So גמרא says והא
קלוניתא עוף טמא הוא, ve'ha'kalanisa uf tamei hu, קלוניתא kalanisa is a
non-kosher bird. ואמר רב, ve'amar Rav, and רב says, טמאה, temeia, when
it's a non-kosher animal or non-kosher bird, בין בחייה בין במיתתה במשהו.
bein be'chayyei bein be'misasa be'mashehu. Everybody agrees if you eat an entire
non-kosher animal, ant, bird, whatever, that you transgress if you do not
need a כזית. kezayis. So we're obviously talking about kosher birds. So
גמרא says אלא כעין קלוניתא. ela k'ein kalanisa. Fine, it would be
some kosher bird that would be like a קלוניתא. kalanisa. So we
don't know if any one exists, but the point is it's not
completely impossible and that's the scenario. Again, all of this was some
somersaults we had to do because of what he called, because of
the question about assuming that you had to eat a whole כזית
kezayis of the אבר, not a כזית kezayis of meat, a כזית
kezayis of the אבר. But the simple sense is the אבר alone
is enough and that certainly is consistent with our general intuitions and
assumptions about בריה. biryah. Okay, now says the גמרא,
where are we?
Now it gets actually a little bit easier. אמר רב, אם תמצא
לומר סבר רבי מחשבת אוכלים שמה מחשבה. im timtza lomar savar Rebbi
machsheves ochalim shemah machshavah. Were we to say that רבי, right, רבי
who says if you eat the whole thing you don't transgress, says
that the way you think about eating should have an impact on
how you define what you've eaten. So therefore,
חישב לאוכלה אבר אבר ואכלה כולה כחיי. chisheiv le'ochlah eiver eiver ve'achlah
kullah k'chayyei. If while it's alive you're thinking to yourself, mm, I
can't wait till I get that pulka from that chicken, okay, and
then you swallow the whole, so since in your mind you've already,
you subjectively have now framed it as אברים, evarim, then רבי would
admit that when you ate it it's considered אבר מן החי. So
this is very inter- or many אברים, evarim, but yeah, but anyway,
but as a בריה biryah I don't know if you could say,
anyway, I'm not sure. Anyway, but this is interesting because this gets
to the whole issue of objective definition versus subjective, and as was
mentioned yesterday and also becomes important in things like יום כיפור Yom
Kippur and whatever, there's a principle of אחשווי, achshavei, notice this phrase
מחשבת אוכלים, machsheves ochalim, but the way אחשווי achshavei is used is
more. something that the ראש Rosh and gets developed later, which is
something that's not considered ראוי לאכילה, raoy l'achila, and the fact, or
actually it's much more of an issue by פסח Pesach and medicine,
it's much less, but not יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, but anyway, it's
something that's not ראוי לאכילה, raoy l'achila, but the fact that you
eat it, you've now defined it as food. So that's taking something
as non-food and you subjectively maybe defining it as food by virtue
of eating it. This is similar but not the same. This is
not a question of is it food or not food, it's do
you look at it as subdivided into limbs or not? But still
it is paying attention to your subjective framing about how you define
food. And let's just finish this up.
אה שוין. ah shoin.
Yeah, not the same. Okay. Anyway, אמר ליה אביי, amar lei Abaye,
so said אביי, Abaye, אביי Abaye doesn't like this. ומי איכא מידי
דאילו אכלה אחר לא מחייב? umi ika midi d'ilu achla acher lo
mechayev? אביי Abaye doesn't like subjective definitions. How could you say that
this chicken, if somebody else were now to eat it, they wouldn't
transgress? Because for another person it's not defined as limbs. ואכלה האי
מחייב? v'achla hai mechayev? And if you eat it, you do transgress
because you defined it? Alright. אמר ליה, amar lei, so רבא said
back, yeah, זה לפי מחשבתו וזה לפי מחשבתו. zeh lefi machshavto v'zeh
lefi machshavto. Each one goes according to their subjective perspective. For you
that you don't have anything particular in mind, we say the norm
is it's not limbs. If I have a different definition, it goes
by me. He's not bothered by different standards for different people. Well,
but that's, yeah, but that's about the weight of the transgression, not
about the fact of the transgression. Okay, but the, you know, how,
but okay, so meaning, now let's just do the same thing in
reverse and with that we'll end.
Quiet. Let's just two more minutes.
ואמר רבא, v'amar Rava, אם תמצא לומר im timtza lomar סבר רבי
אלעזר ברבי שמעון מחשבת אוכלים שמה מחשבה, savar Rebbe Elazar b'Rebbe Shimon
machsheves ochlim shma machshava, the opposite. רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rebbe Elazar
b'Rebbe Shimon says that a normal chicken walking around is already subdivided
into limbs. But if he were to hold that your subjective intention
matters, you could reverse it the other way. So חישב לאוכלה מיתה,
chishev l'ochla misa, if you're looking at that chicken and you're saying,
oh, I can't wait till I שחט shacht it and then I'll
eat it, but you're not looking at it alive as, mmm, what
a yummy פליגל, fliegel, you know, as it's walking around, you're sort
of planning about what it's going to be when it's dead, but
not alive. So now you have undefined it as subdivided into limbs.
Then ואכלה חיה פטור. v'achla chaya patur. Then if you ate it
whole, then you would actually be exempt because now, based on your
subjective perspective, you no longer look at it as limbs, you look
at it as a living, breathing chicken. אמר ליה אביי, amar lei
Abaye, said אביי Abaye again, ומי איכא מידי דאילו אכלה אחר מחייב
ואכלה האי פטור? umi ika midi d'ilu achla acher mechayev v'achla hai
patur?
How can you say that somebody else who eats it transgresses because
for a normal person it's looked at as limbs, but for you,
you don't transgress? אמר ליה, amar lei, yeah, זה לפי מחשבתו וזה
לפי מחשבתו. zeh lefi machshavto v'zeh lefi machshavto.
This one goes according to his perspective, that one goes according to
his
perspective, each one their own subjective definition defines how to look at
this animal. But again, that is something that הלכה halacha normally, normally
הלכה halacha really sides with אביי. Abaye. Normally הלכה says you have
one standard about how we are going to look at something. It's
pretty rare that subjective standards, you know, redefine just for that person.
Okay, we will end here, pick up tomorrow. Have a good יום
כיפור. Yom Kippur. What? Now יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. Yeah, people, we
have, I'm sorry.